Pape Norbert

Kottbusser Damm 79, 10967 Berlin

 1 +49 (0)177 2470874 | ■ norbertpape111@gmail.com | Ш December 26th, 1981 | 🤻 norbertpape.github.io | IG



Personal Profile

Since 2006, Norbert Pape has been working internationally as a dancer, choreographer, pedagogue, creative coder and cultural activist upon having completed a M.A. in Choreography and Performance and a B.A. in Classical and Contemporary Dance. Recently graduated M.Sc. in Mathematics, with specialization in mathematical logic and theoretical computer science.

He has partcipated in, designed and implemented numerous cultural events of varying scale. Besides making an performing in stage works worldwide, he curated and managed festivals, co-founded and ran a center for independent Creation and Research (Z-Zentrum) and been actively involved in shaping the funding policies of the city of Frankfurt am Main as a co-founder and board member od ID Frankfurt e.V..

Education

KU Leuven

M.Sc. in Mathematics (2022)

Freie Universität

B.Sc. in Mathematics (2020)

Justus Liebig Universität

M.A. in Choreography and Performance (2015)

Hochschule für Musik und Darstellende Kunst

Diplom in Classical and Contemporary Dance (2006)

Master Thesis

Presheaf models of Dependent type theory

• Master thesis in the field of mathematical logic and theoretical computer science, on presheaf models of dependent type theory. This new field of research is currently leading to a reformulation of the foundations of mathematics and to great advances in programming language design, in particular with respect to their safety and soundness.

On solitude and the format of the solo

• A reflection on the history of the format of the dance solo. At its core, the solo deals with the political problem of Unity, the philosophical problem of the One and the phenomenological problem of the Self, and therefore also *per se* with being together.

Work Experience

Dancer, Choreographer

- See the news sections of the personal website for detailed information of events of the past 12 months, and the following pages with a list of tour dates of the works he has been dancing in.
- June 2023: Premiere of "Digit(al) on touching Clouds" at the Moovy Filmfestival Köln with consecutive presentation at the New Now Festival.
- February 2023: Premiere of ""O#2"" with students of the Hochschule für Musik und Darstellende Kunst Frankfurt am Main.
- September 2021: Premiere of "O" at the Hamburger Bahnhof.
- Oct. 2018: Choreography for "David Et Jonathas" at the St. Elizabeth Kirche (Berlin).
- His work has been presented in museums and venues such as Theater im Depot Dortmund, Mousonturm Frankfurt, Frankfurt LAB, Schwankhalle Bremen, PACT Zollverein, Festspielhaus Sankt Poelten, Theater Altenburg-Gera, Elizabeth-Kirche Berlin. 2019 / Moving in Concert / Tänzer /
- 2019-2024: Creation and performance with Mette Ingvartsen of Moving in Concert with ongoing tour throughout Belgium, France, Netherlands, Sweden, Germany, Spain, Denmark, Finnland and USA.
- 2017-2023: Creation and performance with Mette Ingvartsen of to come (extended) with ongoing tour throughout Europe, USA and East Asia.
- 2016-2024: Creation and performance with Noé Soulier of Faits et Gestes with ongoing tour throughout Europe.
- 2015-2019: Creation and performance with Mette Ingvartsen of 7 Pleasures with tour throughout Europe, USA and East Asia.
- 2006 today: Numerous further collaborations with internationally acclaimed choreographers such as Franziska Aigner, Simon Speiser, Göksu Kunak, Pêdra Costa, William Forsythe, Nancy Stark Smith, Antje Pfundtner, Jan Ritsema, Bojana Cvejic and Dieter Heitkamp.

August 1, 2023

Coding and art

- Currently preparing a new XR piece for the (Virtual) Ecologies in the Field of Dance symposium
- Juli 2023: Robotics development for Simon Speiser's light sculpture La Vision del Monte.
- Mai 2023: XR piece: Digit(al) on touching digital objects. Premiere at the Moovy Filmfestival Köln, further presentation in the frame of the New Now festival
- · Ongoing collaboration with the Berlin based artist duo OBLIQUE SENSATIONS on VR-related theater projects

Stipends, Symposiums and Conferences

- Upcoming: Virtu(re)al bodies, Symposium of the Gesellschaft für Tanzforschung, October 2023
- 2021, "Gruppen, Ringe, Körper", 3 months research grant, FONDS DAKU
- 2021, "Neue Volkstänze", 2 months research grant, NPN Stepping Out
- 2022, "On Repair and Gathering", two months research grant, FONDS DAKU
- 2023, "XR Schnittstelle zur Darstellenden Kunst", 3 months research grant, FONDS DAKU
- 2022, 6 week VR residency Beyond Gravity, Dortmund
- 2016, The Future of education, Firenze, Italy

Cultural activist

- 2021, he founded International Agency for Space Affairs (IASA), which claims space for life. It recruits experts in space exploration to support the development and dissemination of knowledge, cultural practices and technologies that benefit life on Earth.
- Since 2017, he has been offering regular dance and math courses at the Neue Nachbarschaft Moabit and Strand Tegelsee Zentrum für Erholung und Kultur, in particular for children and teenagers with migration background.
- Active member of Performing Arts Forum, a place for professional and not-yet professional practitioners and activists in the field of performing
 arts, visual art, literature, music, new media and internet, theory and cultural production, and scientists who seek to research and determine
 their own conditions of work.
- Co-founder (2009) and member of the board of ID Frankfurt e.V. (until 2015), an association of freelance choreographers aiming at fostering the development of contemporary dance in Frankfurt am Main and region. Close collaboration with local and regional private and public funding bodies and cultural institutions. In 2021, the association received the prestigious Binding Kulturpreis

Pedagogy through dance

- Dance seminar for Master students in Math pedagogy at the Technische Universität München.
- Worked for a 5 year pilot program in developing educational programs based on the arts in schools in Frankfurt am Main. Funded by the ALTANA Kulturstiftung and supported by the Forsythe Company.

Publications

"Une autoréflexivité qui suscite le questionnement" Interview avec Norbert Pape, danseur contemporain

Interviewed by Jean-Louis Georget, retrievable here

"Using Low Cost Audio-Visual Recording Equipment for Task-Oriented Approaches to Choreography and Dance with Adolescents

download

"Dear colleagues and friends"

edited by Bojana Cvejić, Bojana Kunst, and Stefan Hölscher, published by TkH, Journal for Performing Arts Theory, No. 23, Belgrade download

August 1, 2023 2